This is a painting from the 16th century from Lucas Cranach the Elder.
هذه لوحة من القرن 16 للرسام لوكاس كراناش الأكبر.
It shows the famous Fountain of Youth.
و هي تظهر ينبوع الشباب الشهير.
If you drink its water or you bathe in it, you will get health and youth.
إذا شربتم من ماءه أو اغتسلتم فيه، فستحصلون على الصحة والشباب.
Every culture, every civilization has dreamed of finding eternal youth.
كل الحضارات والثقافات قد حلمت بالحصول على الشباب الدائم.
There are people like Alexander the Great or Ponce De León, the explorer,
وهناك أناس مثل الإسكندر الأكبر أو المستكشف بونثي دي ليون،
who spent much of their life chasing the Fountain of Youth.
قضوا جزءا كبيرا من حياتهم في البحث عن ينبوع الشباب.
They didn't find it.
و لم يعثروا عليه.
But what if there was something to it?
ولكن ماذا لو كان خلف هذه الجعجعة طِحْناً؟
What if there was something to this Fountain of Youth?
ماذا لو كان هناك بالفعل ينبوع للشباب؟
I will share an absolutely amazing development in aging research
سأشارككم تطورا مذهلا في أبحاث الشيخوخة
that could revolutionize the way we think about aging
ما قد يصنع ثورة في نظرتنا إلى الشيخوخة
and how we may treat age-related diseases in the future.
وطريقة معالجتنا للأمراض المرتبطة بالشيخوخة في المستقبل.
It started with experiments that showed,
وقد بدأ الأمر بتجارب أظهرت،
in a recent number of studies about growing,
في عدة دراسات حديثة عن النمو،
that animals -- old mice -- that share a blood supply with young mice
أن الحيوانات --الفئران المُسِنَّة-- التي حقنت بدم فئران صغيرة
can get rejuvenated.
يمكن أن يتجدد شبابها.
This is similar to what you might see in humans, in Siamese twins,
وهذا مشابه لما قد تلاحظونه عند البشر، في التوائم الملتصقة،
and I know this sounds a bit creepy.
وأعلم أن هذا الأمر قد يبدو مخيفا قليلا.
But what Tom Rando, a stem-cell researcher, reported in 2007,
و لكن ما نشره توم راندو، الباحث في الخلايا الجذعيه سنة 2007،
was that old muscle from a mouse can be rejuvenated
عن إمكانية تجديد العضلات القديمة لدى الفئران
if it's exposed to young blood through common circulation.
إذا تعرضت بواسطة الدورة الدموية لدم شاب.
This was reproduced by Amy Wagers at Harvard a few years later,
وبعد بضع سنوات أعادة ايمي ويجيرس التجربة في هارفارد،
and others then showed that similar rejuvenating effects could be observed
وقد لوحظ خلال التجارب التي تلت نفس أثار التجدد
in the pancreas, the liver and the heart.
على البنكرياس والكبد والقلب.
But what I'm most excited about, and several other labs as well,
لكن ما يثير حماستي وحماسة عدة مختبرات أخرى،
is that this may even apply to the brain.
هي إمكانية تطبيق التجربة على الدماغ أيضا.
So, what we found is that an old mouse exposed to a young environment
وقد استنتجنا أن فأراً مسناً تعرض لمحيط أصغر سناً
in this model called parabiosis,
ويسمى في هذا النموذج بالتعايش الإلتصاقي،
shows a younger brain --
أظهر دماغاً شاباً --
and a brain that functions better.
دماغاً يعمل بشكل أفضل.
And I repeat:
وأكرر:
an old mouse that gets young blood through shared circulation
أن فأراً مسناً تعرض من خلال دورة دموية مشتركة لدم فأر صغير السن
looks younger and functions younger in its brain.
يبدو أصغر ويظهر وظائف دماغية أفضل.
So when we get older --
لذا عندما نتقدم في السن --
we can look at different aspects of human cognition,
يمكننا مراقبة مختلف مظاهر القدرة المعرفية البشرية،
and you can see on this slide here,
ويمكن أن تلاحظوا في هذه الشريحة،
we can look at reasoning, verbal ability and so forth.
أنه يمكننا مراقبة القدرة على الاستدلال والكلام وغير ذلك.
And up to around age 50 or 60, these functions are all intact,
وإلى غاية سن 50 أو 60، تكون تلك الوظائف مستقرة،
and as I look at the young audience here in the room, we're all still fine.
وبالنظر إلى الشباب الحاضرين، فإننا جميعاً بخير.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But it's scary to see how all these curves go south.
لكن من المخيف رؤية كل تلك الخطوط البيانية تهوي.
And as we get older,
فكلما تقدمنا في العمر،
diseases such as Alzheimer's and others may develop.
كنا عرضة أكثر للإصابة بأمراض كالزهايمر وغيرها.
We know that with age, the connections between neurons --
ونعلم أنه بالتقدم في السن، فإن الوصلات بين الخلايا العصبية --
the way neurons talk to each other, the synapses -- they start to deteriorate;
طريقة اتصال الخلايا العصبية ببعضها، الوصلات العصبية -- تبدأ في التدهور؛
neurons die, the brain starts to shrink,
الخلايا العصبية تموت، فيبدأ الدماغ في الانكماش،
and there's an increased susceptibility for these neurodegenerative diseases.
وبالتالي ترتفع نسبة الإصابة بتلك الأمراض العصبية التنكسية.
One big problem we have -- to try to understand how this really works
أحد أكبرالمشاكل التي تواجهنا -- لمحاولة فهم كيف يحدث ذلك
at a very molecular mechanistic level --
على المستوى الجزيئي والميكانيكي --
is that we can't study the brains in detail, in living people.
هو أنه لا يمكننا دراسة تفاصيل دماغ إنسان حي.
We can do cognitive tests, we can do imaging --
يمكن أن نجري اختبارات عن القدرات المعرفية والتصوير الطبي--
all kinds of sophisticated testing.
وأنواع مختلفة من الاختبارات المتطورة.
But we usually have to wait until the person dies
لكن يكون علينا عادة الانتظار إلى أن يتوفى الشخص
to get the brain and look at how it really changed through age or in a disease.
لنتمكن من دراسة مدى تأثير السنوات أو المرض على دماغه.
This is what neuropathologists do, for example.
وهذه مهمة اختصاصي علم الأمراض العصبية، على سبيل المثال.
So, how about we think of the brain as being part of the larger organism.
لذا، ماذا إن تصورنا أن الدماغ هو جزء من كائن أكبر.
Could we potentially understand more
هل من الممكن أن نفهم أكثر
about what happens in the brain at the molecular level
ما يحدث في الدماغ على المستوى الجزيئي
if we see the brain as part of the entire body?
إن نحن نظرنا إليه كجزء من الجسم كله؟
So if the body ages or gets sick, does that affect the brain?
وبالتالي، إن كان لتقدم الجسم بالعمر أو مرضه تأثير على الدماغ؟
And vice versa: as the brain gets older, does that influence the rest of the body?
والعكس صحيح: هل يؤثر الدماغ بتقدمه في العمر على باقي الجسم؟
And what connects all the different tissues in the body
وما هو الشيء الذي يربط بين مختلف الأنسجة في الجسم
is blood.
إنه الدم.
Blood is the tissue that not only carries cells that transport oxygen, for example,
الدم ليس فقط عامل لنقل الخلايا والأوكسيجين، وعلى سبيل المثال،
the red blood cells,
الخلايا الحمراء،
or fights infectious diseases,
أو يحارب الأمراض المعدية،
but it also carries messenger molecules,
بل ينقل أيضاً المرساليات الجزيئية،
hormone-like factors that transport information
هرمونات مشابهة لعوامل تنقل المعلومات
from one cell to another, from one tissue to another,
من خلية إلى أخرى ومن نسيج لآخر،
including the brain.
بما في ذلك الدماغ.
So if we look at how the blood changes in disease or age,
إذا ما نظرنا إلى كيف يتأثر الدم خلال المرض أو مع التقدم في السن،
can we learn something about the brain?
إذا هل يمكننا معرفة أي شيء حول الدماغ؟
We know that as we get older, the blood changes as well,
فنحن نعلم بأنه مع تقدمنا في السن، فإن الدم يتغير أيضاً،
so these hormone-like factors change as we get older.
وبالتالي، فإن تلك الهرمونات الشبيهة بالعوامل تتغير بدورها.
And by and large, factors that we know are required
وبشكل عام، فإن أعداد العوامل التي نعرف بأنها ضرورية
for the development of tissues, for the maintenance of tissues --
لنمو الأنسجة ولصيانتها --
they start to decrease as we get older,
تبدأ في التناقص مع تقدمنا في السن،
while factors involved in repair, in injury and in inflammation --
في حين أن أعداد العوامل المرتبطة بصيانة الإصابات والإلتهابات --
they increase as we get older.
ترتفع مع تقدمنا في السن.
So there's this unbalance of good and bad factors, if you will.
لذا، فإن هناك خلل في التوازن بين عوامل النمو والصيانة، إن أردتم القول.
And to illustrate what we can do potentially with that,
ولتوضيح ما يمكننا أن نفعله بهذا الأمر.
I want to talk you through an experiment that we did.
أود أن أحدثكم من واقع تجربة أجريناها،
We had almost 300 blood samples from healthy human beings
حصلنا على ما يقارب 300 عينة دم لأشخاص أصحاء
20 to 89 years of age,
بين 20 و89 سنة،
and we measured over 100 of these communication factors,
وقمنا بتحديد ما يفوق 100 عامل اتصال،
these hormone-like proteins that transport information between tissues.
وتلك الهرمونات الشبيهة بالبروتينات والتي تنقل المعلومات ما بين الأنسجة.
And what we noticed first
وأول ما لاحظناه
is that between the youngest and the oldest group,
بين المجموعة الشابة والمجموعة المتقدمة في السن،
about half the factors changed significantly.
أن حوالي نصف العوامل تغيرت بشكل ملحوظ.
So our body lives in a very different environment as we get older,
وبالتالي فإن جسمنا يعيش في بيئة مختلفة كلما تقدمنا بالعمر،
when it comes to these factors.
عندما يتعلق الأمر بهذه العوامل.
And using statistical or bioinformatics programs,
وباستخدام الإحصائية أو برامج المعلومات البيولوجية،
we could try to discover those factors that best predict age --
حاولنا اكتشاف العوامل التي تؤشر على السن --
in a way, back-calculate the relative age of a person.
وبطريقة ما، أعدنا تقدير السن النسبي لكل شخص.
And the way this looks is shown in this graph.
وكانت النتيجة كما هو ظاهر في المبيان.
So, on the one axis you see the actual age a person lived,
وتشاهدون على أحد المحاور السن الفعلي الذي عاشه الشخص،
the chronological age.
العمر الزمني.
So, how many years they lived.
أي عدد السنوات التي عاشها.
And then we take these top factors that I showed you,
ثم نأخذ تلك العوامل الرئيسية التي أريتكم لها،
and we calculate their relative age, their biological age.
ونحسب عمرها النسبي، والبيولوجي.
And what you see is that there is a pretty good correlation,
وتلاحظون أنهما متطابقين بشكل كبير،
so we can pretty well predict the relative age of a person.
وبالتالي يمكننا التنبؤ بشكل دقيق نسبياً بالسن النسبي للشخص.
But what's really exciting are the outliers,
لكن أكثر ما يثير الاهتمام هي الحالات الاستثنائية،
as they so often are in life.
كما هو الحال دائماً في الحياة.
You can see here, the person I highlighted with the green dot
يمكنكم ملاحظة، الشخص بالنقطة الخضراء
is about 70 years of age
يبلغ حوالي 70 سنة
but seems to have a biological age, if what we're doing here is really true,
لكن يبدو أنه يملك سن بيولوجي، إن لم نخطئ،
of only about 45.
لشخص عمره 45 سنة.
So is this a person that actually looks much younger than their age?
فهل هو شخص يبدو أصغر من سنه الفعلي؟
But more importantly: Is this a person who is maybe at a reduced risk
والأهم: هل هو شخص أقل عرضة ربما
to develop an age-related disease and will have a long life --
لخطر الإصابة بأمراض الشسخوخة وهل سيعمر طويلاً --
will live to 100 or more?
هل سيعيش 100 سنة أو أكثر؟
On the other hand, the person here, highlighted with the red dot,
ومن جهة أخرى، الشخص هنا بالنقطة الحمراء،
is not even 40, but has a biological age of 65.
لم يبلغ 40 سنة حتى، ولكن عمره البيولوجي هو 65 سنة.
Is this a person at an increased risk of developing an age-related disease?
فهل هو شخص عرضة لخطر الإصابة بأمراض الشيخوخة؟
So in our lab, we're trying to understand these factors better,
لذا قمنا في المختبر، بمحاولة فهم أفضل لتلك العوامل،
and many other groups are trying to understand,
وهناك غيرنا العديد ممن يحاولون فهم
what are the true aging factors,
ما هي العوامل المسؤولة عن التقدم في العمر،
and can we learn something about them to possibly predict age-related diseases?
وهل يمككنا معرفة المزيد عنها للتنبؤ بالعمر
So what I've shown you so far is simply correlational, right?
ما عرضته عليكم إلى الآن هو عبارة عن تطابق بين البيانات، صحيح؟
You can just say, "Well, these factors change with age,"
ويمكنكم القول: "حسنا، هذه العوامل تتغير مع العمر،"
but you don't really know if they do something about aging.
لكنكم لا تعرفون إن كانت فعلا لها علاقة بالتقدم في العمر.
So what I'm going to show you now is very remarkable
لذا، ما سأعرضه عليكم الآن هو أمر مدهش
and it suggests that these factors can actually modulate the age of a tissue.
وهي بيانات تفترض بأنه يمكن لتلك العوامل بالفعل تعديل عمر النسيج.
And that's where we come back to this model called parabiosis.
وعند هذه النقطة نعود إلى النموذج المسمى بالتعايش الإلتصاقي.
So, parabiosis is done in mice
جربنا التعايش الإلتصاقي على الفئران
by surgically connecting the two mice together,
عن طريق عملية لاتحاد فأرين معاً،
and that leads then to a shared blood system,
مما يؤدي إلى تشاركهما في نظام دورة دموية واحدة،
where we can now ask, "How does the old brain get influenced
وهنا يمكن أن نسأل: "كيف يتأثر دماغ الفأر المسن
by exposure to the young blood?"
عند تعرضه لدم فأر أصغر سناً؟"
And for this purpose, we use young mice
ومن أجل هذا الغرض، استخدمنا فأرا في سن
that are an equivalency of 20-year-old people,
يعادل شخصاً عمره 20 سنة،
and old mice that are roughly 65 years old in human years.
وفأر في سن يعادل شخصاً عمره 65 سنة.
What we found is quite remarkable.
وكانت النتيجة جد مدهشة.
We find there are more neural stem cells that make new neurons
حيث اكتشفنا أن هناك خلايا جذعية عصبية أكثر تقوم بإنتاج خلايا عصبية جديدة
in these old brains.
في دماغ الفأر المسن.
There's an increased activity of the synapses,
كما أن هناك ارتفاع في نشاط الوصلات العصبية،
the connections between neurons.
الترابط بين الخلايا العصبية.
There are more genes expressed that are known to be involved
وأن هناك تعبيرات جينية أكثر معروفة بكونها تتدخل
in the formation of new memories.
في تكوين الذاكرات الجديدة.
And there's less of this bad inflammation.
وهناك التهاب أقل.
But we observed that there are no cells entering the brains of these animals.
لكننا لاحظنا أنه ليست هناك خلايا تدخل إلى دماغ الحيوان.
So when we connect them,
لذا عندما وصلنا بينهما،
there are actually no cells going into the old brain, in this model.
لم تنتقل أي خلايا إلى دماغ الفأر المسن في هذا النموذج.
Instead, we've reasoned, then, that it must be the soluble factors,
بل نعتقد أن الأمر يتعلق بالعوامل القابلة للذوبان، زما،
so we could collect simply the soluble fraction of blood which is called plasma,
وعليه يمكننا فقط جمع العنصر القابل للذوبان من الدم وهو البلازما
and inject either young plasma or old plasma into these mice,
وحقن سواء بلازما فأر صغير أو مسن في تلك الفئران،
and we could reproduce these rejuvenating effects,
ونتمكن من إعادة إنتاج تلك الآثار المجددة للشباب،
but what we could also do now
بل أصبح بمقدورنا اليوم
is we could do memory tests with mice.
اختبار ذاكرة الفئران.
As mice get older, like us humans, they have memory problems.
وكالبشر، تعاني الفئران مع تقدمها بالعمر من مشاكل الذاكرة.
It's just harder to detect them,
لكن يصعب علينا ملاحظتها،
but I'll show you in a minute how we do that.
لكني سأكشف لكم في دقيقة كيف قمنا بذلك.
But we wanted to take this one step further,
لكن أردنا التقدم أكثر،
one step closer to potentially being relevant to humans.
والاقتراب من إمكانية جعلها ملائمة للبشر.
What I'm showing you now are unpublished studies,
وما سأعرضه عليكم الآن هي دراسات لم تنشر بعد،
where we used human plasma, young human plasma,
حيث استخدمنا بلازما بشرية، لشخص شاب،
and as a control, saline,
وللتحكم محلول ملحي،
and injected it into old mice,
وحقنا بها فأرا مسنا،
and asked, can we again rejuvenate these old mice?
وتسألنا هل بمقدورنا إعادة الشباب إليه؟
Can we make them smarter?
هل يمكننا جعله أكثر ذكاء؟
And to do this, we used a test. It's called a Barnes maze.
وللإجابة، أجرينا اختباراً يدعى متاهة بارنيز
This is a big table that has lots of holes in it,
وهي طاولة كبيرة بها حفر كثيرة،
and there are guide marks around it,
وتحتوي على علامات إرشادية،
and there's a bright light, as on this stage here.
ومضاءة بمصابيح، كإنارة المنصة هنا.
The mice hate this and they try to escape,
والفئران تكره ذلك وتحاول الهرب،
and find the single hole that you see pointed at with an arrow,
والعثور على الحفرة المشار إليها بالسهم،
where a tube is mounted underneath
حيث يوجد أنبوب في الأسفل
where they can escape and feel comfortable in a dark hole.
يمكنها الهرب من خلاله والاسترخاء في الحفرة المظلمة.
So we teach them, over several days,
وخلال عدة أيام،
to find this space on these cues in the space,
دربناها للتعرف على الإشارات فوق الطاولة،
and you can compare this for humans,
ويمكنكم مقارنة هذا الاختبار لدى البشر،
to finding your car in a parking lot after a busy day of shopping.
بالعثور على السيارة في موقف سيارات بعد يوم طويل من التسوق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Many of us have probably had some problems with that.
على الأرجح أن العديد منا عانى من بعض المشاكل في يوم كهذا.
So, let's look at an old mouse here.
دعونا نرى ماذا فعل الفأر المسن هنا.
This is an old mouse that has memory problems,
هذا فأر مسن يعاني من مشاكل في الذاكرة،
as you'll notice in a moment.
وكما ستلاحظون.
It just looks into every hole, but it didn't form this spacial map
فهو اكتفى بالنظر في كل حفرة، دون اعتماد خريطة لمحيطه
that would remind it where it was in the previous trial or the last day.
يمكنه تذكرها من محاولته السابقة أو من آخر يوم حاول فيه.
In stark contrast, this mouse here is a sibling of the same age,
وفي تناقض صارخ، هذا الفأر هو أخ للأول ولديهما نفس السن،
but it was treated with young human plasma for three weeks,
لكنه حقن ببلازما شخص شاب لمدة 3 أسابيع،
with small injections every three days.
بمعدل حقن صغيرة كل 3 أيام.
And as you noticed, it almost looks around, "Where am I?" --
وكما تلاحظون، فهو كمن ينظر حوله ويتساءل: "أين أنا؟" --
and then walks straight to that hole and escapes.
ويمشي مباشرة نحو الحفرة الهدف ويهرب.
So, it could remember where that hole was.
إذا، فقد تمكن من تذكر مكان الحفرة.
So by all means, this old mouse seems to be rejuvenated --
لذا وبكل ما تحمله الكلمة من معنى، يبدو أن هذا الفأر المسن قد استعاد شبابه --
it functions more like a younger mouse.
وهو يتصرف أكثر كفأر صغير السن.
And it also suggests that there is something
وهذا يفترض أيضا بأن بلازما الفأر الصغير السن
not only in young mouse plasma, but in young human plasma
وكذا بلازما الشخص الشاب تحتوي على شيء ما
that has the capacity to help this old brain.
بملك القدرة على مساعدة الدماغ المسن.
So to summarize,
وخلاصة القول،
we find the old mouse, and its brain in particular, are malleable.
وجدنا أن دماغ الفأر المسن دماغ طيع.
They're not set in stone; we can actually change them.
ليسا متحجرين؛ في الواقع يمكننا تغييرهما.
It can be rejuvenated.
يمكن إعادة الشباب إليه.
Young blood factors can reverse aging,
يمكن للعوامل الموجودة بالدم الشاب أن تعكس الشيخوخة،
and what I didn't show you --
وما لم أعرضه عليكم --
in this model, the young mouse actually suffers from exposure to the old.
في هذا النموذج، أن الفأر الصغير يعاني من تعرضه لدم فأر مسن.
So there are old-blood factors that can accelerate aging.
وعليه هناك عوامل بالدم المسن تسرع من الشيخوخة.
And most importantly, humans may have similar factors,
والأهم، أنه قد يكون لدى البشر نفس تلك العوامل،
because we can take young human blood and have a similar effect.
لأننا نحصل على نفس التأثير باستخدامنا لدم شخص شاب.
Old human blood, I didn't show you, does not have this effect;
ولم أخبركم أيضا بأن دم شخص مسن ليس له ذلك التأثير؛
it does not make the mice younger.
فهو لا يجعل الفئران تصغر بالسن.
So, is this magic transferable to humans?
فهل هذا السحر قابل للتطبيق على البشر؟
We're running a small clinical study at Stanford,
نجري حاليا دراسة سريرية في ستانفورد،
where we treat Alzheimer's patients with mild disease
حيث نعالج مرضى الزهايمر في مراحل مبكرة
with a pint of plasma from young volunteers, 20-year-olds,
بنصف لتر من البلازما يتبرع بها متطوعون عمرهم 20 سنة،
and do this once a week for four weeks,
وذلك مرة كل أسبوع وخلال 4 أسابيع،
and then we look at their brains with imaging.
ونراقب تفاعل أدمغتهم بواسطة التصوير الطبي.
We test them cognitively,
حيث نختبرهم معرفياً،
and we ask their caregivers for daily activities of living.
ونسأل مقدمي الرعاية المسؤولين عنهم عن أنشطتهم اليومية.
What we hope is that there are some signs of improvement
وما نرجوه هو ظهور بعض مؤشرات التحسن
from this treatment.
من تلقي هذا العلاج وإن نجح الأمر،
And if that's the case, that could give us hope
فإن ذلك سيمنحنا الأمل
that what I showed you works in mice
بأن ما نجح مع الفئران
might also work in humans.
قد ينجح أيضا مع البشر.
Now, I don't think we will live forever.
الحقيقة أنا لا أظن بأننا سنعيش للأبد.
But maybe we discovered
لكن ربما نكون قد اكتشفنا
that the Fountain of Youth is actually within us,
بأن ينبوع الشباب هو في الواقع موجود بداخلنا،
and it has just dried out.
وقد جف للتو.
And if we can turn it back on a little bit,
وإن تمكنا من جعله يتدفق ولو لوقت قصير،
maybe we can find the factors that are mediating these effects,
فلربما نتمكن من العثور على العوامل الناقلة لتلك التأثيرات،
we can produce these factors synthetically
لننتجها بشكل صناعي
and we can treat diseases of aging, such as Alzheimer's disease
وسنتمكن من معالجة أمراض الشيخوخة كمرض الزهايمر
or other dementias.
أو غيرها من أمراض الخرف.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)